<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Paul Bricman</title>
    <description>My thoughts on cognitive science, academia, and society.
</description>
    <link>https://paubric.github.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://paubric.github.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 07:25:29 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 07:25:29 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Feynman Cluster</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever considered joining a community for the sole purpose of meeting like-minded people? Have you ever been encouraged to join such communities in order to find members who share your interests? Well, I know I have. Meet-ups for people interested in machine learning. Online groups for people interested in software development. Group chats for people interested in personal knowledge management. All those communities are built on the premise that if you group like-minded people together, you get a comfortable environment where healthy discussions can take place. That’s a reasonable argument, but is there anything missing? Is like-mindedness the best catalyst for healthy discussions, or is it actually limiting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One possible drawback of such a community is the fact that members are all familiar with the topic. Why is this a drawback? Well, if people are familiar with it, they are less likely to question it. Their similar background knowledge becomes implicit. Everyone assumes that this is how things are naturally going. There’s no “Wait, I don’t get it, why do you actually do that?” or “This doesn’t make sense, how does this follow?”. There’s no incentive for critical thinking when people don’t bat an eye to underlying assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another drawback of a like-minded community is the problem of limited perspectives. If members have a similar background, they’ll likely have similar views on the topic at hand. Even with a minority of members with diverging views, the culture which forms around a topic leaves its homogeneous mark on the community. At the same time, many of the world’s toughest challenges require the collaboration between different fields and schools of thought. The pieces of humanity’s greatest puzzles aren’t to be found in any one particular field, but in a rich network of radically different ones. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/mental-models/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; from Farman Street puts this nicely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here’s another way to think about it. When a botanist looks at a forest they may focus on the ecosystem, an environmentalist sees the impact of climate change, a forestry engineer the state of the tree growth, a business person the value of the land. None are wrong, but neither of them are able to describe the full scope of the forest. Sharing knowledge, or learning the basics of the other disciplines, would lead to a more well-rounded understanding that would allow for better initial decisions about managing the forest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if, instead of creating communities based on similar interests, we created communities based on &lt;em&gt;dissimilar&lt;/em&gt; ones? Despite the reluctance, disparate fields will often prove converging because of the highly interconnected nature of human knowledge. Get together an architect, a doctor, a developer, a lawyer, an entrepreneur, a researcher, a teacher, a social worker, an accountant, and others, and incentivize them to explain things to each other. Let’s term this resulting community a &lt;em&gt;Feynman cluster&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This configuration solves both previously-mentioned problems. Each person will have to constantly explain themselves in front of the others, as they can’t rely on any implicit domain-specific knowledge anymore. Moreover, because the rest are not familiar with the content, they’ll be able to easily probe the other’s knowledge for gaps and inconsistencies in the process of understanding. What’s more, due to the fact that they have different interests, they’ll likely have different views on many topics, which enables them to gain a rich collective understanding of a wide variety of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might think of a torrent platform as an analogy for a Feynman cluster. Each member brings their own knowledge to the table, and they can tap into the whole entirety of the others’ knowledge in return. However, this analogy does not capture a unique property of such a community. On a torrent platform, it’s only considered fair that users balance the amount of content they provide (seed) with the amount of content they receive (leech). If a user accesses way more content than they offer, then they’re cheating. In contrast, in a Feynman cluster, members benefit from both tapping into the collective knowledge &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; from sharing their own knowledge. Why? Because of the Feynman technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you know a lot about a topic and you’re talking with someone who doesn’t, you’re forced to systematically break down concepts, clearly explain the relations between them, and provide representative examples. Not only is this useful for your interlocutor, but it is also very beneficial for you. Trying to explain a topic forces you to extract its essence from the noise, helping you realize what actually defines it. It forces you to seek the fundamental principles, and it brings to light the shaky parts of your knowledge in the process. This is extremely valuable, as it incentivizes you to further develop your own knowledge, despite the fact that you’re not interacting with new information per se, just looking at it differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering this, it can be said that a Feynman cluster is a positive-sum game. Everyone benefits from sharing knowledge. People routinely switch between the role of the teacher and the role of the student, and they gain value from both. Compare this to a torrent platform, where you wouldn’t directly benefit from sharing information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concretely, Feynman clusters might take on various shapes and sizes. For example, such a community could consist of a group chat of highschool friends who went on to study different things in university. It could also be based on an online group where users have flairs describing their background (e.g. economics, medicine, architecture) and moderators (or bots) incentivize discussion between users with different backgrounds. It could also take the form of a meet-up with dynamically changing topics, which might consist of small-group and plenary discussions. There’s still a need for a reason to bring everyone together, but once that is settled, thought-provoking discussions can start to take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like-minded communities and Feynman clusters are not in conflict. You could be part of communities of both types. However, time spent in one means time not spent in the other. This, together with the enhanced comfort of hanging around like-minded people, may prevent many from experimenting with Feynman clusters. Therefore, there’s a need for actively trying things out beyond the comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, we are social creatures with extensive collective knowledge, and we also individually benefit from explaining things to each other. Why not combine the two in order to build a community like the Feynman cluster?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 07:16:24 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://paubric.github.com/tools%20for%20thinking/2020/10/02/the-feynman-cluster.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://paubric.github.com/tools%20for%20thinking/2020/10/02/the-feynman-cluster.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Tools for Thinking</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Willpower as Setting</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;willpower-as-force&quot;&gt;Willpower as Force&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re all familiar with the notion of willpower resembling a force that you can exercise. A force that you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; exercise on your life so as to achieve your goals. It’s so pervasive, this idea of individuals with complete agency wielding the power of will in order to navigate the challenges of life, that we barely question it. However, as with other meritocratic ideals, it has downsides. Not meeting your expectations may make you think that you &lt;em&gt;lack&lt;/em&gt; the willpower, that you’re not worthy. But is there something to lack in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;willpower-as-setting&quot;&gt;Willpower as Setting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Willpower is just another name for the idea of choosing long-term outcomes rather than short-term ones.&lt;/em&gt; —  António R. Damásio&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came across this concise quote in Damásio’s book &lt;em&gt;Descartes’ Error&lt;/em&gt;, a seminal piece of work about the interaction between reason and emotion. Damásio takes a different perspective on willpower and describes it as a matter of &lt;em&gt;choice&lt;/em&gt;, rather than a force. And I think it’s brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about it, every situation which we associate with willpower contains a choice to be made. If you’re trying to get fit, will you choose the benefit of a healthy body which you could obtain in several months, or the relief of not having to go to the gym tomorrow? If you’re trying to learn how to play an instrument, will you choose the benefit of having mastered the skill in several months, or the relief of not having to struggle with the next practice session? If you’re trying to quit smoking, will you choose future health or the satisfaction of having a cigarette? You get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reframing of willpower as a choice, rather than a force, makes for a gentler and more accessible path to making healthy decisions. It might seem less intimidating to see willpower as a “setting” in your cognitive configuration, as it avoids the notion of having to exercise a force, having to make efforts, or having to use your power. The same way you would turn on the Do Not Disturb setting on your phone to block distractions, you’d turn it on for your life. Of course, these are just two ways of talking about the same thing, because you could very well argue that it takes a force to change these settings. Still, this may prove as a useful perspective, because it allows us to detach from the setting itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/dnd.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you make prior commitments, it’s surprisingly easy to lose sight of the long-term outcomes because the short-term ones are obstructing your view. It’s easy to forget the &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; behind what you’re doing, the very objective of your actions. At the same time, there are effective ways in which you can remind yourself that there’s a forest beyond the trees of busywork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to bring the long-term in sight is to set up actual reminders. You could extend your morning routine to include a brief refresher on your current objectives. You could place inspiration in clear sight. This could be a quote of someone you admire from your field of interest, a picture of one such person, or something else entirely. As a student of artificial intelligence, my dream is to create intelligent machines, so I found the following quote fitting for my home screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It will be no less important than the creation of the intelligence that created it.&lt;/em&gt; — Ray Kurzweil, futurist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to keep in mind your long-term objectives is to remind yourself about the commitment you have been respecting so far. The whole streak idea. Remind yourself of the investments of time and energy you’ve already put into pursuing these objectives. Whether the objectives are the right ones is a different topic entirely, but thinking of your progress so far can still help you stick to them. Is it worth it to throw away all that you achieved up to this point? Take that into account when making the choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, besides reminding yourself of your objectives and of your progress towards them so far, you could keep track of the very process of getting closer and closer to them. Congratulate yourself regularly on the shrinking distance between your current state and your goal state. Sprinkle achievements at various checkpoints on your way to the objectives in order to incentivize yourself to further shorten that distance. Those are a reflection of both the fact that you’ve come a long way and that you’re getting closer everyday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recap, using willpower can be seen as making choices between short-term and long-term outcomes, rather than exercising a force. Even better, we can use various strategies in order to bring the long-term in sight and make more educated decisions, including: remembering your objectives, becoming aware of your progress so far, and realizing that you’re getting closer by day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mountain.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s your turn now. How would you bring your own objectives in sight so that you don’t get blinded by day-to-day tasks?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 08:58:44 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://paubric.github.com/tools%20for%20thinking/2020/09/26/willpower-as-setting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://paubric.github.com/tools%20for%20thinking/2020/09/26/willpower-as-setting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Tools for Thinking</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Pocket Philosopher</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Child:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Why is the sky blue?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parent:&lt;/strong&gt; Because of the way sunlight passes through Earth’s atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Child:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;What’s an atmosphere?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parent:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s like a thin blanket placed around a planet. Ours is made of air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Child:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Why is there an atmosphere?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parent:&lt;/strong&gt; You know what? I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have heard such a dialogue between a parent and a child before. You may have even been lucky enough to experience it first-hand already. Or rather unlucky, depending on who you ask. Most people describe the experience as annoying or unpleasant. That’s not surprising. The child, in his or her relentless pursuit towards making sense of the world, comes to you for answers. The child is eager to learn, and therefore starts probing your knowledge for useful insights into how the world works. In the process, he or she might uncover important gaps or inconsistencies in your knowledge, which can range from uncomfortable to embarassing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A famous person who went around asking such questions (and annoying people in the process) was Socrates. The ancient greek philosopher would walk around and start asking people trivial questions. However, he would systematically follow up with more and more questions, trying to probe the other’s reasoning for inconsistencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Socrates:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;With what is rhetoric concerned?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gorgias:&lt;/strong&gt; With discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Socrates:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;What sort of discourse, Gorgias — such discourse as would teach the sick under what treatment they might get well?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gorgias:&lt;/strong&gt; No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Socrates:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Then rhetoric does not treat of all kinds of discourse?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gorgias:&lt;/strong&gt; Certainly not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Socrates:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;And yet rhetoric makes men able to speak?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gorgias:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Socrates:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;And to understand that about which they speak?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gorgias:&lt;/strong&gt; Of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Socrates&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Come, then, and let us see what we really mean about rhetoric…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, going around and annoying people with a never-ending onslaught of questions got him put on trial and eventually killed. However, the Socratic method eventually became the basis for many techniques of critical thinking. By using a systematic way of posing questions aimed at bringing to light the assumptions and thought process behind a statement, the Socratic method became a timeless tool for helping people think more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why those sequences of questions are annoying is that they uncover gaps and inconsistencies in our knowledge. If ignorance is bliss, the Socratic method is misery. We evolved to perceive consistency as pleasant and inconsistency as painful. But the very reason why the Socratic method is painful is also why it is so incredibly powerful. Bringing the discrepancies in your knowledge to light is an important first step in becoming aware of them, so that you can eventually fix them. We should be honest with ourselves regarding our knowledge, because only then will we be able to develop it effectively. We should make a habit out of going beyond the cognitive dissonance of being challenged and slowly improve our reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An honest man is always a child. —&lt;/em&gt; Socrates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the Socratic method consists of posing tough questions, but what kind of questions specifically? We could classify those based on their goal. For example, a question might be designed to challenge assumptions, like “&lt;em&gt;Is this always the case?&lt;/em&gt;” or “&lt;em&gt;Why do you think that this assumption holds here?&lt;/em&gt;”. Other questions might be asked to make you think about alternative ways to approach a problem, like “&lt;em&gt;Can you look at this in another way?”&lt;/em&gt; or “&lt;em&gt;What is the counter-argument?&lt;/em&gt;”. Yet other questions might help you explore consequences, like “&lt;em&gt;If this was indeed the case, what would be the implications?&lt;/em&gt;” or “&lt;em&gt;What would be the result of this?&lt;/em&gt;”. All these questions challenge your knowledge in one way or another. And they’re quite effective, which is why we still extensively use Socrates’ practices across countless fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think about it, the questions themselves are not that complex. You probably had no trouble understanding what they mean. Therefore, we have in our hands a set of tools which are not only very powerful, but they’re also very simple to understand and use. The difficult part in harnessing the Socratic method is not in creating thought-provoking questions, but rather in creating the right context for the dialogue to manifest effectively. You don’t need domain-specific knowledge yourself in order to challenge domain-specific knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings up an opportunity: what if we could create a tool for thinking based on the Socratic method? Building it would be rather straight-forward, because posing these questions is simple. What matters is the context that is being created, the conversation. Even better, there’s already a mature class of tools designed to hold conversations with people. We call them chatbots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/chat.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A session with a Socratic chatbot would unfold as follows. Whenever you’re in for a critical thinking exercise, you would open up a chat with it and tell it what you think. This could be a concept you’re trying to grasp, a societal problem you’re trying to solve, a personal issue you’re trying to tackle, or anything you are trying to get a better grasp on. Then, the chatbot would answer with plain questions designed to challenge your thinking, shift your attention to alternative perspectives, and look for evidence. In other words, it would guide you in thinking critically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; The sky is blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;What makes you think that’s the case?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; Personal observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Is this always the case?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, others report similar observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;What is the underlying cause of this?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe it’s the sunlight that’s being reflected off the oceans and back into the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Is this always the case?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; Not really, because the sky is blue even in the middle of the countryside, far from the sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Can you look at this in another way?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe it’s because of the water in our atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;If this was indeed the case, what would be the implications?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; The sky wouldn’t be blue in places that are extremely dry, like the desert. But the sky is also blue in there, so yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Is this always the case?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; I mean, I’ve never heard of the sky not being blue in the desert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Can you look at this in another way?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe it’s because of the way sunlight interacts with our atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Is there evidence to support this?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; Well, white light interacts with a prism in funny ways, so maybe that’s what’s happening here as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Can you elaborate on that?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe the atmosphere is sort of acting like a giant prism, making the sky seem blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the chatbot simply spit out random questions from a tiny collection might get repetitive. A more pleasant conversation partner might require adding more powerful natural language processing capabilities. This would make the chatbot able to pose questions which include your messages as context, like in the dialogues at the beginning. Instead of responding with predefined strings, it would use templates which adapt to the topic of discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; The sky is blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;What makes you think that the sky is blue?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; Personal observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chatbot:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Is it always the case that the sky is blue?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, others report similar observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we wouldn’t expect such chatbots to exhibit intelligent behavior. That isn’t their purpose, and would be far beyond their capabilities. However, even such an algorithmic agent could still prove useful, because, as we’ve seen before, one could challenge the subject at hand without having a grasp on it. The real value of such a chatbot would be in probing your own knowledge, the knowledge of the interlocutor, in a more systematic manner. And even if the conversation becomes a bit clumsy at times, this doesn’t diminish its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would you discuss with such a chatbot? How far would the discussion go? Those are intriguing questions waiting for answers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 07:42:23 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://paubric.github.com/tools%20for%20thinking/2020/09/20/the-pocket-philosopher.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://paubric.github.com/tools%20for%20thinking/2020/09/20/the-pocket-philosopher.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Tools for Thinking</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Darwin Meets Moses</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;darwin&quot;&gt;Darwin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why the planets in our solar system are moving in such an orderly manner? Their orbits are so neatly arranged in (roughly) concentric circles, and they are all (generally) moving in one single plane. Why aren’t they whirling around chaotically, like some cosmic misbehaved children?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was amazed to learn that the answer to this question is the same as the one which explains how complex life managed to appear back here on Earth: evolution. Planets are under the selective pressure of natural selection as well, just as living things. If the planets moving around a star would have disorderly orbits that intersect each other, they would simply smash themselves out of existence. The population of planets in our solar system &lt;em&gt;evolved&lt;/em&gt; into what we observe today: a tidy formation of polite cosmic adults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/planets.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept on being amazed to learn that a lot of other seemingly unrelated phenomena can be explained by the same reasoning. Companies are under selective pressure to make profit, and therefore markets evolve to contain profitable companies. Online content is under selective pressure to gain your attention, and therefore social media platforms evolve to contain attention-grabbing content. The list goes on and on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particularly fascinating domain in which this evolutionary rationale can be applied is in ideas. Any idea, really. Ideas live. We keep them alive by &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt; them. However, we can’t think of that many things at the same time. Ideas die out, because we lose interest in them. There are scarce resources in this cognitive ecosystem in which ideas proliferate. However, ideas also &lt;em&gt;spread&lt;/em&gt;. I can tell you about an idea in writing, then you can tell someone about it through speech, and so on. In a sense, the idea is creating offspring, it is reproducing itself into other people’s minds. Ideas &lt;em&gt;evolve.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a moment to appreciate the complexity of our world. Planets evolved to not smash into each other. On at least one of them, complex life evolved to not die. Across multiple species, ideas evolved to not be forgotten. All this, with probably countless more levels beneath, above, and in parallel. An interconnected symphony of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s explore the evolutionary operators which drive this proliferation of ideas. First and foremost, there is natural selection, caused by selective pressure. Ideas that are not &lt;em&gt;thinked&lt;/em&gt; will eventually die out. But what makes an idea more thought of? What makes a fit individual of the population of ideas? The function of fitness for an idea may be determined by a combination of factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, is it appealing? We usually stay with ideas that we like, that are compatible with our existing belief systems. An idea that is profoundly incompatible with our belief systems would cause cognitive dissonance, a painful sensation of inconsistency in our minds. We evolved to avoid that, and that’s why it’s painful. We also like when things &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt;, when there is suddenly a harmonious consistency in our worldview. Keep in mind that the evolved population of humans is actually the &lt;em&gt;environment&lt;/em&gt; for the population of ideas. Therefore, ideas that are appealing to us are more likely to stick around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, is it helpful? Ideas that cause counterproductive ways of thinking would harm their hosts. But ideas can’t survive without them. Therefore, ideas that are harmful are at a disadvantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, is it contagious? There are ideas that we feel like sharing. Of course, these ideas have an evolutionary advantage: they manage to spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another operator which facilitates evolution in general is mutation. A tiny chance of individuals changing in a subtle way. When you tell me an idea, and I misunderstand it, I obtain an idea that is different than yours. This can be seen as an error in reproduction, which is a common source of mutation in biological evolution as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, another important one is cross-over. It refers to the way in which parents create an offspring that is a combination of the two. With ideas, you can think of the situation in which you connect multiple ideas and give rise to a new one. A cognitive psychologist might call this process convergent creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/operators.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fascinating to see how the same mechanics that supported the development of complex life on Earth can be applied to the proliferation of ideas in human culture. It’s even more fascinating to think about &lt;em&gt;ideologies.&lt;/em&gt; These are belief systems, or maybe… “societies” of ideas: a whole new level of complexity above ideas, just like human societies emerge from humans. They are collectively subject to the same evolutionary operators, but in a deeper way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;moses&quot;&gt;Moses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An influential species of ideologies are religions. For thousands of years, they have caused both torment and ecstasy in human culture. Many religions are often at odds with evolutionary thinking, and creationism versus evolutionism is still a fierce debate. However, we can think of creationism, and religions as a whole, as a product of ideologic evolution, and in so doing reconcile the two sides of the debate in a mutually-compatible worldview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Widespread religions seem to also fit the criteria for fit individuals based on selective pressure. They are appealing because they provide consistency in our reasoning, they provide attractive causal explanations for phenomena in the outside world and in our personal lives. That’s why it happened, because this deity wanted to punish you. That’s how it all came about, so-and-so deity created the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re also usually (but definitely not always) helpful. For example, jews follow the Kosher rules for eating. These prescribe some general guidelines for food. For example, they prohibit the consumption of pork. If you think about it, that’s quite a good rule of thumb, because eating a lot of red meat is detrimental to your health. One might imagine a religion which dictated counterproductive ways of living, for example eating a lot of pork. Such a religion would be at an evolutionary disadvantage because it is harmful for its followers, it is damaging its environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religions also spread. Most of the popular religions evolved intricate rituals for dominating cognitive territory. In most religions, parents are encouraged to pass on their religious heritage to their child. Another widespread practice is when religions constrain their followers to marrying someone with the same religion, which pressures many to convert. A religion without missionaries wouldn’t proliferate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It therefore makes sense why religions, especially the ones that are currently popular, are so widespread. They are quite appealing, usually helpful, and very contagious. Maybe it was inevitable for such ideologies to develop on the foundation of human thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see yourself on team Darwin as opposed to team Moses, take a few moments to ponder the complex evolutionary dynamics which may have given rise to the ideologies you are interacting with. You’re on the same team.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 14:23:55 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://paubric.github.com/philosophy/2020/09/13/darwin-meets-moses.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://paubric.github.com/philosophy/2020/09/13/darwin-meets-moses.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Philosophy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>After Science</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Reality is complex. We, as humans, seek to better understand it. Why? Because knowing how the world works can inform better standards of living, can satisfy socioeconomic interests, and, last but not least, because it’s fun. There’s this thrill of the hunt for answers to our most difficult questions. What pulls us towards the ground? What causes a rich harvest? What makes us sick? How come that we are here in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But reality is chaotic, and we’ve had quite some trouble grasping its infinite complexity. Therefore, in pursuing a better understanding, we set out to build models. Simplified descriptions of how the world works. Models describing the movements of the stars. Models describing the unfolding of weather. Models describing the underlying components of matter. These models are far from being perfect, but they manage to provide a decently accurate picture of the real thing. We embraced models because they are manageable, they consist of mathematical equations, numerical tables, clear taxonomies, fundamental principles etc. We know how to deal with those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did we build them? How did we keep on improving them? By making sure that the models provide a description of reality that is as close as possible to the ground truth. A model predicts that the stars will move as they will actually do, the weather will unfold as it actually will etc. Scientists used their intuition to fine-tune models so that they got closer and closer to perfectly describing the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It worked great. Putting people on the surface on the moon, connecting people on the internet, curing countless diseases. However, we are still clueless about many things, and our models are a long way from being perfect descriptions of reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-curious-situation&quot;&gt;A Curious Situation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now guide you through a different, but ultimately converging, train of thought. There are many fields in which we managed to build agents which outperform humans at various tasks, albeit in specific conditions. For example: object detection software is better at detecting objects than humans, speech recognition software is better at transcribing speech than humans, and computer vision software is better at diagnosing medical imaging than humans. How do these agents work? We probably used the scientific method to iteratively propose more and more accurate models of, for example, human speech, right? Wrong. We don’t know how these agents work. We didn’t provide them with a unified theory of human speech. We don’t understand the theories they seem use. Many people find that confusing, even unsettling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we didn’t incorporate our well-earned domain-specific knowledge into these agents, how do they manage to not only rise to human performance, but even often go beyond that? The answer is that we made them able to learn by themselves. We taught them how to fish, instead of giving them the fish. We created models that are able to optimize themselves, without domain-specific human guidelines. They fine-tune themselves based on empirical data, based on the ground truth of reality. It is an ongoing effort based on algebra, statistics, calculus, engineering, and other fields, but we’re getting there, slowly but surely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s pretty neat, isn’t it? We managed to build models that can eventually incorporate very powerful descriptions of reality. What’s the problem? The problem is that we don’t know how they work. We can apply them in spectacular industrial feats, but we don’t know how they do it. We understand how the optimization process generally works, because we built it, but we can’t grasp the result, the final model. There’s no linguist on the planet that understands the complexity of the speech recognition model after optimization. But, at the same time, we are able to wield its power in practical applications. An interesting situation we find ourselves in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bitter-lesson&quot;&gt;The Bitter Lesson&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important approach to Artificial Intelligence is based on the creation of models of the human mind. Rich Sutton, a distinguished researcher in AI who’s been active in the field for several decades, expressed an intriguing observation in a short essay called &lt;a href=&quot;http://incompleteideas.net/IncIdeas/BitterLesson.html&quot;&gt;The Bitter Lesson&lt;/a&gt;. In it, he describes the limited success of models whose knowledge was explicitly articulated by humans compared to models which started with zero domain-specific knowledge, only to learn by themselves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The actual contents of minds are tremendously, irredeemably complex; we should stop trying to find simple ways to think about the contents of minds, such as simple ways to think about space, objects, multiple agents, or symmetries. All these are part of the arbitrary, intrinsically-complex, outside world. They are not what should be built in, as their complexity is endless; instead we should build in only the meta-methods that can find and capture this arbitrary complexity. Essential to these methods is that they can find good approximations, but the search for them should be by our methods, not by us. We want AI agents that can discover like we can, not which contain what we have discovered. Building in our discoveries only makes it harder to see how the discovering process can be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, until recently, scientific models where created by scientists themselves, with no intermediate entity. Now, in a growing number of fields, there are general models which outperform any human-made alternative, and we didn’t even have to tell them how to do it. What gives? How can we reconcile the respectable track record of human-made models with the outstanding performance of self-improving models? To answer that question we may have to rethink how we do science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-new-way&quot;&gt;A New Way?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the traditional research cycle, scientists start by proposing a research question and a hypothesis, a tentative answer to the initial question. Then, they design a method of testing whether the hypothesis really is the answer to the question. They conduct the tests, analyze the results, and finish with a bit of reflection on the study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, the hypothesis describes a specific way in which things presumably are, a way in which reality &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. They may sound like: “Students who eat breakfast will perform better on a math exam than students who do not eat breakfast”, “Drinking sugary drinks daily leads to obesity”, or “Roses watered with liquid Vitamin B grow faster than roses watered with liquid Vitamin E”. The problem is that from the very beginning of a study, the proposed models are influenced by the researchers themselves. But they are only human, and therefore the models that later developed are strongly influenced by humans. We have seen that this is not the only way of building powerful models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How about instead of the researchers proposing a hypothesis in the very first stage of the study, they limit themselves to just posing the research question? Then, they throw in a general model that is expressive enough to capture the complex dynamics of reality in the context of the problem at hand. Finally, they extract the hypothesis &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; the optimized model. The model takes on a big chunk of the responsibilities of the researcher, but the latter doesn’t lose her job, because she can now move her efforts to &lt;em&gt;interpreting&lt;/em&gt; the optimized model, rather than building it from the ground up. The student becomes the master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications&quot;&gt;Implications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a humbling idea, moving past the paradigm of humans incrementally improving their models of reality through the scientific method. It means accepting that reality is maybe a bit too complex for our minds to comprehensively grasp. It means recognizing that algorithms can incorporate a better understanding of reality into models than we can. It sure is a bitter lesson, but it may just be a powerful new way of driving human progress. Instead of trying to simplify the complexity of reality, we fight fire with fire: we throw complex general models at it which can get it right, even if we don’t understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it worth it? It largely depends on what you think the ultimate purpose of science is. If you think that the goal of conducting research is to eventually &lt;em&gt;apply&lt;/em&gt; it, you should get excited that we can now use these general models in practical applications. The end justifies the means, just skip the human scientists. If you think that the goal of science is for humanity to gain a deeper understanding of reality, then there’s a bumpy road ahead, because interpreting such complex models seems to be a challenging thing in itself. If you think that science is just for fun, brace yourselves because this paradigm shift will surely be one hell of a ride.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 10:44:13 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://paubric.github.com/philosophy/2020/09/05/after-science.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://paubric.github.com/philosophy/2020/09/05/after-science.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Philosophy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fragrances of Memories Past</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-richness-of-smell&quot;&gt;The Richness Of Smell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all experienced it. A hint of perfume which reminds you of a past lover. The aroma of a dish which takes you back to childhood for a few delightful moments. The scent of a room which calls up rich experiences which unfolded there. Smell has a uniquely powerful connection to memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smell is also a very rich sense. Due to the fact that it was an early innovation from an evolutionary perspective compared to other senses, it is rooted deep into our nervous system. And it shows. Recent studies estimate that humans are capable of distinguishing among more than a trillion scents. If you were to smell one every second, you would still have hundreds of billions left at the end of your lifetime. Compare this to the perception of color, estimated at around a hundred million shades. That’s several orders of magnitude lower. Perception of sound pitch is even less precise, with only several thousands of frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iconic neurologist Oliver Sacks described the compelling case of a person experiencing hyperosmia, a heightened sense of smell:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I found each one unique, evocative, a whole world.” He found he could distinguish all his friends by smell: “I went into the clinic, I sniffed like a dog, and in that sniff recognized, before seeing them, the twenty patients who were there. Each had his own olfactory physiognomy, a smell-face, far more vivid and evocative, more redolent, than any sight-face.” He could smell their emotions — fear, contentment, sexuality — like a dog. He could recognize every street, every shop, by smell — he could find his way around New York, infallably, by smell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we could leverage these unique properties of smell in order to inform powerful memorization techniques? What if scents could help us organize and manage our memories so that we could tap into them more efficiently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;leveraging-smell&quot;&gt;Leveraging Smell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now trivial to capture the &lt;em&gt;visual&lt;/em&gt; aspect of our experiences. We grab our phone and take a picture.  However, capturing the &lt;em&gt;olfactive&lt;/em&gt; side of experiences turns out to be much more difficult. Camera sensors capture one thing: light. Our noses, on the other hand, have to sense billions of different molecules. That turned out to be quite an engineering feat, as creating machines that sense smell as precisely as we do are still years away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that wasn’t enough, smell not only is more difficult to &lt;em&gt;detect&lt;/em&gt; than sight, but it is also harder to reproduce. We often go back and look over pictures in order to remind ourselves of past times. Even apps designed solely for storage of pictures incorporate &lt;em&gt;looking back&lt;/em&gt; features by prompting you with the pictures you took a year ago, for instance. What hardware does this require? Screens. They emit one thing: light. However, if we were to reproduce a specific smell, we would need a tiny biochemical lab. All this, in your pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, if it’s difficult to both capture and reproduce smell, how can we still use its powerful connection to memory to our advantage? A promising direction is the idea of intentionally bringing an external scent into an experience in order to create an association with it. This would translate to using a known substance with a specific smell during a moment you want to later recall. That known substance may be anything from a commercial perfume to a scented candle. It could even be a substance specifically created for the purpose of the memory technique we are building. The only requirement is that you know how to procure more of it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would it be a priority for it to be easy to procure? Because this would easily enable an aided recollection further down the road. If you used a specific scented candle when you read a book, you might want to stock up on it when you want to recall that experience. If you used a specific perfume on a trip, you might want to keep some of it for when you want to look back on it in a vivid way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, you can use scents as &lt;em&gt;tags&lt;/em&gt;. External cues which you add onto a piece of information in order to retrieve it in a more orderly manner. That piece of information may be a fact, an experience, or something else entirely. Just procure more of the scent later and enjoy the throwback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/fragrances.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you plan on using many of these tags in your memory technique, you might try to be systematic about maximizing the number of scents you can bring to life based on a limited pool of substances. You might try to collect a few powerful scents which you would then combine with each other in many ways. For example, binary combinations of 20 different scents can be used to create over a million combinations, plenty for safely tagging your favorite experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rich world of sensation awaits, its potential untapped. What kind of experiences would afford tagging in your life? What would your olfactive tags be?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 10:44:13 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://paubric.github.com/tools%20for%20thinking/2020/08/22/fragrances-of-memories-past.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://paubric.github.com/tools%20for%20thinking/2020/08/22/fragrances-of-memories-past.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Tools for Thinking</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The World Is Your Mind Palace</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Few memorization techniques have attracted as much attention as the Mind Palace. Famously being used by Sherlock Holmes, it is far from being fiction. It is a well-established memorization technique which links one’s knowledge with the tangible structure of a palace. However, there are strong reasons why the palace should go &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; the mind. This way, it can be a bridge between your knowledge and your material environment, a powerhouse of associations between radically different aspects of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mind-palace&quot;&gt;The Mind Palace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mind Palace technique itself has several flavors. The most popular one consists of mentally navigating a space that is familiar to you, say a park, and populating it with knowledge you want to store. This may translate to visualizing related diagrams and scenes at specific spots of that space. By mentally interweaving the familiar place with the new information, you are creating a robust method of accessing knowledge in a systematic manner. The place is your launching pad into knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other variants of this method include visualizing a completely new space, rather than a familiar one. This may be something traditionally associated with storing knowledge, such as a library. You would define sections, corridors, shelves, and so on, so that the organization of the space would match the taxonomy of the content you are storing. One final twist includes a combination of the first two: an imaginary place, say a palace, which houses several real spaces, such as rooms from your home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these techniques are limiting in one important aspect. Why restrict yourself to imagining these places, when you can directly immerse yourself in them as part of the learning process? Why choose to acquire knowledge by associating it with a visualization, when you can strengthen the association with the real deal, in vivid reality? Of course, the reason may be the ease of accessing the mental representation of the given place, but perception often outmatches visualization in terms of vividness. This advantage may be key to developing a more powerful memorization technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-embodied-mind-palace&quot;&gt;The Embodied Mind Palace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of a real place are elementary, as Sherlock might put it. It might serve as the very context of acquiring information, a background which would already do the work of creating associations with knowledge for you. If your mind palace is based on a park, you might consider turning learning episodes into walks in the park. Conversely, you might wander around it and retrieve information associated with specific spots. These accessible routines provide effective means to strengthen the foundation of your palace so that it persists over years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Maintaining an Embodied Mind Palace is literally a walk in the park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the familiar environment which is the basis for your palace is more than a blank canvas ready to be cultivated with knowledge, it is a rich library of personal experience. We have a tendency to learn things easier when they tie into our personal lives in a powerful way, and a &lt;em&gt;familiar&lt;/em&gt; place is, by definition, a place that is relevant to us. Interweaving experiences with knowledge is a powerful way in which the Embodied Mind Palace exploits the self-reference effect, further improving its effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another advantage of the Embodied Mind Palace over a vanilla one is the rich experience of the palace across senses. Taking a walk in the park would most likely engage your visual, auditory, and olfactive senses, as well as your proprioceptive, spatial, and tactile ones. The many modes of perception would serve as diverse links between the palace and the information, providing yet even more powerful associations. In contrast, mental images are less vivid. Some people even experience aphantasia, a condition which completely impairs their ability to form mental images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/park.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, we have explored a host of new benefits brought about by the Embodied Mind Palace: accessibility, self-reference, and multimodality. Together, they pertain an exciting twist on the original technique. However, the new flavor is not only more brain-friendly, but it even creates new opportunities for technology to lend a helping hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools-for-the-architect&quot;&gt;Tools For The Architect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology can help make the associations between places and information more explicit. You can actively use it as a means of strengthening the foundation of your palace. The most exciting part: this technology is relatively new and still developing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to explicitly superimpose knowledge onto a familiar place is by using AR technology, short for alternate reality. These tools enable you to do things like drawing in mid-air with a wide range of colors and textures by only using your phone. Many AR apps also allow you to place images, text, and various 3D objects in the virtual layer of the space around you. Explicitly seeing content in the very location you choose as the basis for your palace helps solidify associations. This can be a formula, a flowchart, a mind map, a picture, a quote, a chart, or any other form of content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to emphasize the connection between a location and a piece of information is to use geofences. These are virtual boundaries around an area which your phone can be configured to detect. By using geofences, you can grant yourself permission to access a piece of content only when you are located in a specific area. By turning these places into exclusive pathways to knowledge, you are further strengthening the mnemonic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final way in which technology can facilitate the construction and maintainance of your mind palace is through map builders. These tools are used by people who are creating worlds from the ground up, like fiction writers and game designers. They provide the means to visually articulate the layout of a fictional world in an epic way. Imagine using your phone to navigate between The Valley of Integrals and The Fields of Derivatives, all while passing through a sacred spot which signifies the relation between the two mathematical concepts, say The Altar of The Fundamental Theorem of Calculus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of today, there is no piece of software available which incorporates all the previously mentioned technologies. Therefore, there’s a lot of space for developers to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Embodied Mind Palace is an exciting twist on the original memory technique, providing a host of benefits and opportunities. How will your palace look like?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 10:44:13 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://paubric.github.com/tools%20for%20thinking/2020/08/07/the-world-is-your-mind-palace.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://paubric.github.com/tools%20for%20thinking/2020/08/07/the-world-is-your-mind-palace.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Tools for Thinking</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
