<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Paul Bricman</title>
    <description>My thoughts on cognitive science, academia, and society.
</description>
    <link>https://paulbricman.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://paulbricman.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 13:02:48 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 13:02:48 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>After Science</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about this a lot lately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reality is complex. We, as humans, seek to better understand it. Why? Because knowing how the world works can inform better standards of living, can satisfy socioeconomic interests, and, last but not least, because it’s fun. There’s this thrill of the hunt for answers to our most difficult questions. What pulls us towards the ground? What causes a rich harvest? What makes us sick? How come that we are here in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But reality is chaotic, and we’ve had quite some trouble grasping its infinite complexity. Therefore, in pursuing a better understanding, we set out to build models. Simplified descriptions of how the world works. Models describing the movements of the stars. Models describing the unfolding of weather. Models describing the underlying components of matter. These models are far from being perfect, but they manage to provide a decently accurate picture of the real thing. We embraced models because they are manageable, they consist of mathematical equations, numerical tables, clear taxonomies, fundamental principles etc. We know how to deal with those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did we build them? How did we keep on improving them? By making sure that the models provide a description of reality that is as close as possible to the ground truth. A model predicts that the stars will move as they will actually do, the weather will unfold as it actually will etc. Scientists used their intuition to fine-tune models so that they got closer and closer to perfectly describing the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It worked great. Putting people on the surface on the moon, connecting people on the internet, curing countless diseases. However, we are still clueless about many things, and our models are a long way from being perfect descriptions of reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-curious-situation&quot;&gt;A Curious Situation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now guide you through a different, but ultimately converging, train of thought. There are many fields in which we managed to build agents which outperform humans at various tasks, albeit in specific conditions. For example: object detection software is better at detecting objects than humans, speech recognition software is better at transcribing speech than humans, and computer vision software is better at diagnosing medical imaging than humans. How do these agents work? We probably used the scientific method to iteratively propose more and more accurate models of, for example, human speech, right? Wrong. We don’t know how these agents work. We didn’t provide them with a unified theory of human speech. We don’t understand the theories they seem use. Many people find that confusing, even unsettling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we didn’t incorporate our well-earned domain-specific knowledge into these agents, how do they manage to not only rise to human performance, but even often go beyond that? The answer is that we made them able to learn by themselves. We taught them how to fish, instead of giving them the fish. We created models that are able to optimize themselves, without domain-specific human guidelines. They fine-tune themselves based on empirical data, based on the ground truth of reality. It is an ongoing effort based on algebra, statistics, calculus, engineering, and other fields, but we’re getting there, slowly but surely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s pretty neat, isn’t it? We managed to build models that can eventually incorporate very powerful descriptions of reality. What’s the problem? The problem is that we don’t know how they work. We can apply them in spectacular industrial feats, but we don’t know how they do it. We understand how the optimization process generally works, because we built it, but we can’t grasp the result, the final model. There’s no linguist on the planet that understands the complexity of the speech recognition model after optimization. But, at the same time, we are able to wield its power in practical applications. An interesting situation we find ourselves in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bitter-lesson&quot;&gt;The Bitter Lesson&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important approach to Artificial Intelligence is based on the creation of models of the human mind. Rich Sutton, a distinguished researcher in AI who’s been active in the field for several decades, expressed an intriguing observation in a short essay called &lt;a href=&quot;http://incompleteideas.net/IncIdeas/BitterLesson.html&quot;&gt;The Bitter Lesson&lt;/a&gt;. In it, he describes the limited success of models whose knowledge was explicitly articulated by humans compared to models which started with zero domain-specific knowledge, only to learn by themselves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The actual contents of minds are tremendously, irredeemably complex; we should stop trying to find simple ways to think about the contents of minds, such as simple ways to think about space, objects, multiple agents, or symmetries. All these are part of the arbitrary, intrinsically-complex, outside world. They are not what should be built in, as their complexity is endless; instead we should build in only the meta-methods that can find and capture this arbitrary complexity. Essential to these methods is that they can find good approximations, but the search for them should be by our methods, not by us. We want AI agents that can discover like we can, not which contain what we have discovered. Building in our discoveries only makes it harder to see how the discovering process can be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, until recently, scientific models where created by scientists themselves, with no intermediate entity. Now, in a growing number of fields, there are general models which outperform any human-made alternative, and we didn’t even have to tell them how to do it. What gives? How can we reconcile the respectable track record of human-made models with the outstanding performance of self-improving models? To answer that question we may have to rethink how we do science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-new-way&quot;&gt;A New Way?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the traditional research cycle, scientists start by proposing a research question and a hypothesis, a tentative answer to the initial question. Then, they design a method of testing whether the hypothesis really is the answer to the question. They conduct the tests, analyze the results, and finish with a bit of reflection on the study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, the hypothesis describes a specific way in which things presumably are, a way in which reality &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. They may sound like: “Students who eat breakfast will perform better on a math exam than students who do not eat breakfast”, “Drinking sugary drinks daily leads to obesity”, or “Roses watered with liquid Vitamin B grow faster than roses watered with liquid Vitamin E”. The problem is that from the very beginning of a study, the proposed models are influenced by the researchers themselves. But they are only human, and therefore the models that later developed are strongly influenced by humans. We have seen that this is not the only way of building powerful models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How about instead of the researchers proposing a hypothesis in the very first stage of the study, they limit themselves to just posing the research question? Then, they throw in a general model that is expressive enough to capture the complex dynamics of reality in the context of the problem at hand. Finally, they extract the hypothesis &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; the optimized model. The model takes on a big chunk of the responsibilities of the researcher, but the latter doesn’t lose her job, because she can now move her efforts to &lt;em&gt;interpreting&lt;/em&gt; the optimized model, rather than building it from the ground up. The student becomes the master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications&quot;&gt;Implications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a humbling idea, moving past the paradigm of humans incrementally improving their models of reality through the scientific method. It means accepting that reality is maybe a bit too complex for our minds to comprehensively grasp. It means recognizing that algorithms can incorporate a better understanding of reality into models than we can. It sure is a bitter lesson, but it may just be a powerful new way of driving human progress. Instead of trying to simplify the complexity of reality, we fight fire with fire: we throw complex general models at it which can get it right, even if we don’t understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it worth it? It largely depends on what you think the ultimate purpose of science is. If you think that the goal of conducting research is to eventually &lt;em&gt;apply&lt;/em&gt; it, you should get excited that we can now use these general models in practical applications. The end justifies the means, just skip the human scientists. If you think that the goal of science is for humanity to gain a deeper understanding of reality, then there’s a bumpy road ahead, because interpreting such complex models seems to be a challenging thing in itself. If you think that science is just for fun, brace yourselves because this paradigm shift will surely be one hell of a ride.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 10:44:13 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://paulbricman.com/academia/2020/09/05/after-science.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://paulbricman.com/academia/2020/09/05/after-science.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>academia</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fragrances of Memories Past</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-richness-of-smell&quot;&gt;The Richness Of Smell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all experienced it. A hint of perfume which reminds you of a past lover. The aroma of a dish which takes you back to childhood for a few delightful moments. The scent of a room which calls up rich experiences which unfolded there. Smell has a uniquely powerful connection to memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smell is also a very rich sense. Due to the fact that it was an early innovation from an evolutionary perspective compared to other senses, it is rooted deep into our nervous system. And it shows. Recent studies estimate that humans are capable of distinguishing among more than a trillion scents. If you were to smell one every second, you would still have hundreds of billions left at the end of your lifetime. Compare this to the perception of color, estimated at around a hundred million shades. That’s several orders of magnitude lower. Perception of sound pitch is even less precise, with only several thousands of frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iconic neurologist Oliver Sacks described the compelling case of a person experiencing hyperosmia, a heightened sense of smell:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I found each one unique, evocative, a whole world.” He found he could distinguish all his friends by smell: “I went into the clinic, I sniffed like a dog, and in that sniff recognized, before seeing them, the twenty patients who were there. Each had his own olfactory physiognomy, a smell-face, far more vivid and evocative, more redolent, than any sight-face.” He could smell their emotions — fear, contentment, sexuality — like a dog. He could recognize every street, every shop, by smell — he could find his way around New York, infallably, by smell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we could leverage these unique properties of smell in order to inform powerful memorization techniques? What if scents could help us organize and manage our memories so that we could tap into them more efficiently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;leveraging-smell&quot;&gt;Leveraging Smell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now trivial to capture the &lt;em&gt;visual&lt;/em&gt; aspect of our experiences. We grab our phone and take a picture.  However, capturing the &lt;em&gt;olfactive&lt;/em&gt; side of experiences turns out to be much more difficult. Camera sensors capture one thing: light. Our noses, on the other hand, have to sense billions of different molecules. That turned out to be quite an engineering feat, as creating machines that sense smell as precisely as we do are still years away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that wasn’t enough, smell not only is more difficult to &lt;em&gt;detect&lt;/em&gt; than sight, but it is also harder to reproduce. We often go back and look over pictures in order to remind ourselves of past times. Even apps designed solely for storage of pictures incorporate &lt;em&gt;looking back&lt;/em&gt; features by prompting you with the pictures you took a year ago, for instance. What hardware does this require? Screens. They emit one thing: light. However, if we were to reproduce a specific smell, we would need a tiny biochemical lab. All this, in your pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, if it’s difficult to both capture and reproduce smell, how can we still use its powerful connection to memory to our advantage? A promising direction is the idea of intentionally bringing an external scent into an experience in order to create an association with it. This would translate to using a known substance with a specific smell during a moment you want to later recall. That known substance may be anything from a commercial perfume to a scented candle. It could even be a substance specifically created for the purpose of the memory technique we are building. The only requirement is that you know how to procure more of it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would it be a priority for it to be easy to procure? Because this would easily enable an aided recollection further down the road. If you used a specific scented candle when you read a book, you might want to stock up on it when you want to recall that experience. If you used a specific perfume on a trip, you might want to keep some of it for when you want to look back on it in a vivid way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, you can use scents as &lt;em&gt;tags&lt;/em&gt;. External cues which you add onto a piece of information in order to retrieve it in a more orderly manner. That piece of information may be a fact, an experience, or something else entirely. Just procure more of the scent later and enjoy the throwback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you plan on using many of these tags in your memory technique, you might try to be systematic about maximizing the number of scents you can bring to life based on a limited pool of substances. You might try to collect a few powerful scents which you would then combine with each other in many ways. For example, binary combinations of 20 different scents can be used to create over a million combinations, plenty for safely tagging your favorite experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rich world of sensation awaits, its potential untapped. What kind of experiences would afford tagging in your life? What would your olfactive tags be?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 10:44:13 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://paulbricman.com/cognitive_science/2020/08/22/fragrances-of-memories-past.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://paulbricman.com/cognitive_science/2020/08/22/fragrances-of-memories-past.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>cognitive_science</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The World Is Your Mind Palace</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a palace in your mind, and you are its architect. Let’s get building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few memorization techniques have attracted as much attention as the Mind Palace. Famously being used by Sherlock Holmes, it is far from being fiction. It is a well-established memorization technique which links one’s knowledge with the tangible structure of a palace. However, there are strong reasons why the palace should go &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; the mind. This way, it can be a bridge between your knowledge and your material environment, a powerhouse of associations between radically different aspects of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mind-palace&quot;&gt;The Mind Palace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mind Palace technique itself has several flavors. The most popular one consists of mentally navigating a space that is familiar to you, say a park, and populating it with knowledge you want to store. This may translate to visualizing related diagrams and scenes at specific spots of that space. By mentally interweaving the familiar place with the new information, you are creating a robust method of accessing knowledge in a systematic manner. The place is your launching pad into knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other variants of this method include visualizing a completely new space, rather than a familiar one. This may be something traditionally associated with storing knowledge, such as a library. You would define sections, corridors, shelves, and so on, so that the organization of the space would match the taxonomy of the content you are storing. One final twist includes a combination of the first two: an imaginary place, say a palace, which houses several real spaces, such as rooms from your home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these techniques are limiting in one important aspect. Why restrict yourself to imagining these places, when you can directly immerse yourself in them as part of the learning process? Why choose to acquire knowledge by associating it with a visualization, when you can strengthen the association with the real deal, in vivid reality? Of course, the reason may be the ease of accessing the mental representation of the given place, but perception often outmatches visualization in terms of vividness. This advantage may be key to developing a more powerful memorization technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-embodied-mind-palace&quot;&gt;The Embodied Mind Palace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of a real place are elementary, as Sherlock might put it. It might serve as the very context of acquiring information, a background which would already do the work of creating associations with knowledge for you. If your mind palace is based on a park, you might consider turning learning episodes into walks in the park. Conversely, you might wander around it and retrieve information associated with specific spots. These accessible routines provide effective means to strengthen the foundation of your palace so that it persists over years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Maintaining an Embodied Mind Palace is literally a walk in the park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the familiar environment which is the basis for your palace is more than a blank canvas ready to be cultivated with knowledge, it is a rich library of personal experience. We have a tendency to learn things easier when they tie into our personal lives in a powerful way, and a &lt;em&gt;familiar&lt;/em&gt; place is, by definition, a place that is relevant to us. Interweaving experiences with knowledge is a powerful way in which the Embodied Mind Palace exploits the self-reference effect, further improving its effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another advantage of the Embodied Mind Palace over a vanilla one is the rich experience of the palace across senses. Taking a walk in the park would most likely engage your visual, auditory, and olfactive senses, as well as your proprioceptive, spatial, and tactile ones. The many modes of perception would serve as diverse links between the palace and the information, providing yet even more powerful associations. In contrast, mental images are less vivid. Some people even experience aphantasia, a condition which completely impairs their ability to form mental images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, we have explored a host of new benefits brought about by the Embodied Mind Palace: accessibility, self-reference, and multimodality. Together, they pertain an exciting twist on the original technique. However, the new flavor is not only more brain-friendly, but it even creates new opportunities for technology to lend a helping hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools-for-the-architect&quot;&gt;Tools For The Architect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology can help make the associations between places and information more explicit. You can actively use it as a means of strengthening the foundation of your palace. The most exciting part: this technology is relatively new and still developing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to explicitly superimpose knowledge onto a familiar place is by using AR technology, short for alternate reality. These tools enable you to do things like drawing in mid-air with a wide range of colors and textures by only using your phone. Many AR apps also allow you to place images, text, and various 3D objects in the virtual layer of the space around you. Explicitly seeing content in the very location you choose as the basis for your palace helps solidify associations. This can be a formula, a flowchart, a mind map, a picture, a quote, a chart, or any other form of content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to emphasize the connection between a location and a piece of information is to use geofences. These are virtual boundaries around an area which your phone can be configured to detect. By using geofences, you can grant yourself permission to access a piece of content only when you are located in a specific area. By turning these places into exclusive pathways to knowledge, you are further strengthening the mnemonic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final way in which technology can facilitate the construction and maintainance of your mind palace is through map builders. These tools are used by people who are creating worlds from the ground up, like fiction writers and game designers. They provide the means to visually articulate the layout of a fictional world in an epic way. Imagine using your phone to navigate between The Valley of Integrals and The Fields of Derivatives, all while passing through a sacred spot which signifies the relation between the two mathematical concepts, say The Altar of The Fundamental Theorem of Calculus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of today, there is no piece of software available which incorporates all the previously mentioned technologies. Therefore, there’s a lot of space for developers to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Embodied Mind Palace is an exciting twist on the original memory technique, providing a host of benefits and opportunities. How will your palace look like?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 10:44:13 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://paulbricman.com/cognitive_science/2020/08/07/the-world-is-your-mind-palace.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://paulbricman.com/cognitive_science/2020/08/07/the-world-is-your-mind-palace.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>cognitive_science</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
